<chapter id="uimlnet-chapter" xreflabel="Tool and Library Overview">
<!--
Copyright (c) 2004 Kris Luyten <kris.luyten@luc.ac.be>.
    Limburgs Universitair Centrum
	Expertisecentrum Digitale Media

    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
    under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
    or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
    with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
    A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
    Free Documentation License".
-->

<title>Uiml.net Tool and Libary Overview</title>
<section>
	<title>Basic Components</title>
	<para>
		Uiml.net is a <emphasis>user interface creation library</emphasis>, that converts a user interface
		described as a UIML file into a working user interface on the .Net virtual machine. Uiml.net
		can be used with multiple widget sets, like <ulink url="http://gtk-sharp.sourceforge.net">Gtk-sharp</ulink>,
		<ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/en-us/cpref/html/frlrfSystemWindowsForms.asp">System.Windows.Forms</ulink> and 
		<ulink url="http://wxnet.sourceforge.net">Wx.NET</ulink>. It is truly multi-platform: it works with <ulink url="http://www.mono-project.com">Mono</ulink>,
		<ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/netframework/">Microsoft .Net Framework</ulink> 
		and <ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/en-us/dv_evtuv/html/etconNETCompactFramework.asp">Microsoft Compact .Net Framework</ulink>.
	</para>
	<para>
		The Uiml.net software is packaged as a set of libraries:
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>uiml.net.dll</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Is the core library: it contains the software that reads and processes an UIML document.
								It can be linked with your application and used from within your application as shown in example <xref linkend="uimlnetlib-example"/>.
								There is also a front-end application the offers a command line interface or a graphical interface for the uiml.net.dll library;
								uiml.net.exe. Uiml.net.dll also contains all the core functionality to render a UIML file, but it 
								can only render the user interface if there is a matching widget set backend available for the widget set that is referenced
								by the UIML vocabulary. Each supported widget-set is packaged as a separate assembly.
							   <example id="uimlnetlib-example">
					          <title>A simple UIML front-end user interface to illustrate Connect</title>
								 <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
UimlDocument uimlDoc = new UimlDocument("myinterface.uiml");
IRenderer renderer =  (new BackendFactory()).CreateRenderer(uimlDoc.Vocabulary);
IRenderedInstance instance = renderer.Render(uimlDoc);
instance.ShowIt();									 
]]>
                         </programlisting>
							   </example>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>uiml-&lt;widgetset&gt;.dll</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								A set of separate assemblies, each containing widget-set specific rendering code. These assemblies are very small,
								since the core functionality is contained in uimnl.net.dll. Currently, uiml-compact-swf.dll, uiml-gtk-sharp.dll,
								uiml-swf.dll and uiml-wx-net.dll can be used. Just drop these in the same directory as uiml.net.dll so the rendering
								library can find them and load them on-demand.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>uiml.net.exe</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								A front-end for the library, that supports easy testing of UIML documents. Both a command-line tool and a graphical
								interface can be used.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
	</para>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Usage of the Front-end</title>
	<para>
		This section discusses how the Uiml.net front-ends can be used to test your UIML documents. For each platform is a front-end available
		that allows you to load a UIML document and render it for the current platform. The front-ends are fairly simple: their task is limited to 
		allow you to load and render the UIML document. Each subsection is devoted to a separate platform that can be used. The front-ends are included 
		in one of the precompiled versions of an uiml.net executable.
	</para>
	<para>
		Notice these front-ends are just to help you to test your UIML files with uiml.net. It is not meant to be deployed with your final application;
		for this purpose you can link with the uiml.net.dll library and bundle it with the preferred back-end(s).
	</para>
	<section>
		<title>Command Line tool</title>
		<para>
			This front-end allows you to specify options for the uiml.net executable on the command line. Just start &ldquo;uiml.net.exe&rdquo; without
			options to see all possible options and a short explanation for each option. You can specify a UIML file and one or more libraries to 
			be linked with your UIML file.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gtk# front-end</title>
		<para>
			This front-end gives you a simple Gtk# front-end to open an UIML file and select one or more libraries that have to be linked with your
			UIML file.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>System.Windows.Forms front-end</title>
		<para>
			This front-end gives you a simple System.Windows.Forms front-end to open an UIML file and select one or more libraries that have to be linked with your
			UIML file.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Compact.Windows.Forms front-end</title>
		<para>
			This front-end gives you a simple Compact System.Windows.Forms front-end to open an UIML file and select one or more libraries that have to be linked with your
			UIML file.
		</para>
	</section>

</section>
</chapter>
